Charles Green Shaw
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Charles Green Shaw papers
1686, 1833-1979, bulk 1909-1974
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Shaw, Charles Green
45.6 linear feet
The collection measures 45.6 linear feet and and documents the life of American abstract artist, writer, poet, and illustrator Charles Green Shaw. The papers date from 1833-1979 with the bulk of the material spanning 1909-1974 and a single item of ephemera dating from 1686. Records include biographical information and correspondence with family, colleagues and several artists and writers. The papers also contain writings and extensive diaries, sketchbooks and scrapbooks spanning Shaw's entire career, scattered financial records and other printed material.
Biographical Note
A significant figure in American abstract art, Charles Green Shaw (1892-1974) enjoyed a varied career as a writer, illustrator, poet, modernist painter, and collector. Born to a wealthy family and orphaned at a young age, Charles and his twin brother were raised by their uncle, Frank D. Shaw. At age nine, he was already an avid painter and had illustrated his first book, The Costumes of Nations.
After Shaw's 1914 graduation from Yale, he attended the Columbia University School of Architecture. In the years before World War I he worked briefly in the real estate business, but was primarily occupied as a member of café society. During the war he was a pilot stationed in England with the American Expeditionary Force's aero squadron.
As a young man, Shaw decided to become a writer and devoted his time and attention to this endeavor for a decade. In the 1920s, Shaw spent extended periods living and writing in London and Paris, and contributed many pieces to publications such as The New Yorker, Smart Set, Vanity Fair and Town & Country. Two of Shaw's novels, Heart In a Hurricane (1927) and The Low Down (1928), were published during this period. His play What Next! was produced in New York in 1928, but its run was brief. Later, he published New York – Oddly Enough (1938), and wrote and illustrated children's books including The Giant of Central Park (1940) and It Looked Like Spilt Milk (1947), in addition to illustrating several more books by other children's authors.
A highly accomplished poet partial to haiku and cinquain, Shaw published three volumes of poetry: Image of Life (1962), Into the Light (1959), and Time Has No Edge (1966). More than 1500 of his poems appeared in numerous American and European poetry magazines. He received the Michael Strange Poetry Award in 1954, and was a member of the Poetry Society (London), American Poets Fellowship Society, and North American Poets.
Shaw studied at the Art Students League in 1926 under Thomas Hart Benton and as a private pupil of George Luks. He became aware of abstract art and its various movements while traveling in Europe in the 1920s. When he began painting seriously in the early 1930s, Shaw drew from what he had seen and learned of modernism in Paris to develop his own style that incorporated American themes and technology. His earliest modern work was in the cubist vein. He constructed Arp-influenced wooden reliefs and the plastic polygon series (1933-1939) that foreshadowed shaped paintings developed by the next generation. Shaw's paintings progressed to hard edged abstractions and a return to figurative work in the 1940s was followed by abstract expressionism. Shaw had few connections with other New York artists, although he was well acquainted with A. E. Gallatin and George L. K. Morris and was a member of American Abstract Artists from its inception.
His first solo exhibition was at Valentine Gallery in 1934; in the following year he had a one man show at Gallatin's Museum of Living Art. Shaw was among the artists included in Gallatin's 1936 show, "Five Contemporary American Conceretionists," originating at the Rienhardt Gallery and then traveling to Galérie Pierre in Paris, and Mayer Gallery in London. He exhibited widely and was represented by Passedoit Gallery and Bertha Schaefer Gallery. Shaw's work can be found in major museum collections including the Museum of Modern Art, Metropolitan Museum of art, Guggenheim Museum, Art Institute of Chicago, Brooklyn Museum, and San Francisco Museum.
Around 1945, Shaw began creating approximately 600 montages that included collage and incorporated early prints, dice, antique playing cards, pipes, and fabrics arranged in shadow boxes. Though many of the montages decorated his apartment, they were never exhibited publicly during his lifetime.
Shaw was an avid collector. Among his collections were antique playing cards; figures, folk art, and implements relating to tobacco; tinsel prints, particularly of theatrical figures; prints and paper ephemera relating to the London theater; horse brasses; and antique police truncheons. In addition, Shaw was an authority on Lewis Carroll about whom he wrote a number of articles.
Charles Green Shaw died in New York City in 1974.
Scope and Content Note
The collection measures 45.6 linear feet and and documents the life of American abstract artist, writer, poet, and illustrator Charles Green Shaw. The papers date from 1833-1979 with the bulk of the material spanning 1909-1974 and a single item of ephemera dating from 1686. Shaw's personal life and career are well documented through biographical information, correspondence, writings, extensive diaries and sketchbooks, scattered financial records, scrapbooks and other printed materials.
Series 1: Biographical Information includes a number of family documents. Shaw's correspondence in Series 2 consists mainly of incoming letters from friends and a small amount of correspondence from notable individuals including Adele Astair, Clarence and Ruby Darrow, F. Scott Fitzgerald, John D. Graham, Anita and John Loos, H. L. Mencken, Robert C. Osborn, Cole Porter, Carl Van Vechten and Walter Winchell. The series also includes some nineteenth century family correspondence.
Among Shaw's writings in Series 3 are 145 diaries containing daily one-page entries that outline his daily schedule. In addition, there are drafts and final manuscripts of fiction, non-fiction, plays, and poems, as well as quizzes devised for his newspaper column, and short writings for magazines. Notes include travel observations, notes on restaurants and nightclubs, notes for fiction, quotations, and lists of his collections. Writings by other authors on a variety of topics include children's books illustrated by Shaw, a review of Shaw's poetry, and an article about Shaw as a modern painter.
Artwork by Shaw in Series 4 includes collages, drawings, and paintings. Of particular interest are 340 sketchbooks containing sketches and finished drawings in pencil and ink, watercolor and gouache paintings, pastels and collages. Among the artwork by other artists is a charcoal portrait, probably of Shaw, by Betty George.
Series 5: Financial Records, consists mainly of banking records, tax returns, and royalty statements. Also included is information about art sales and payment for writings; receipts are for art related expenses and document purchases for Shaw's collection of tobacco figures.
Series 6: Scrapbooks (37 volumes) documents Shaw's entire career. Five volumes concern his art and exhibitions, 9 volumes preserve his published writings, 20 volumes contain published poems, and an additional 5 volumes are devoted to miscellaneous subjects.
Additional printed matter in Series 7: Printed Material, consists of items by Shaw, by other authors, and miscellaneous material. Items by Shaw includes articles, books by and/or illustrated by Shaw, plays, and poems. Printed material by other authors includes pieces about or mentioning Shaw, books, exhibition catalogs and related records, and periodicals. Among the miscellaneous printed material are auction and book catalogs, clippings, and ephemera. Also included are a wide assortment of menus, along with theatrical memorabilia, travel brochures and printed souvenirs collected by Shaw.
Series 8: Miscellaneous Records, consists of a variety of artifacts including the Century Association Art Committee Medal awarded Shaw, a letter opener carved with his monogram, and printing plates for color reproductions of a painting by Shaw and of prints in his collection. Other miscellaneous records are two sound recordings, a tape recording of Shaw reading his poetry, and an unidentified phonograph album.
Series 9: Photographs includes photos of artwork, people, places and miscellaneous subjects. Artwork depicted here is mainly by Shaw, but there are also photographs of work by other artists, and of items in Shaw's collections of tinsel prints and tobacco figures, as well as views of various exhibition installations.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 9 series:
Series 1: Biographical Information, 1874-1970 (Boxes 1, 46, OV 50; 0.2 linear ft.)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1833-1973 (Boxes 1-3; 2.5 linear ft.)
Series 3: Writings, 1910-1971 (Boxes 3-20, 46; 17.5 linear ft.)
Series 4: Artwork, 1929-1974 (Boxes 21-30, 47-47, OV51; 10.15 linear ft.)
Series 5: Financial Records, 1933-1971 (Boxes 30-31; 0.65 linear ft.)
Series 6: Scrapbooks, 1922-1970 (Boxes 31-34, 46; 3.2 linear ft.)
Series 7: Printed Material, 1686-1979 (Boxes 34-41, 46; 7.6 linear ft.)
Series 8: Miscellaneous Records, circa 1890s-circa 1970s (Box 42, packages 53-54; 0.35 linear ft.)
Series 9: Photographs, 1885-circa 1970 (Boxes 42-46, OV 53; 3.45 linear ft.)
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents and under "Names" when they are creators or contributors.
Subjects-Topical:
Painting, Modern -- 20th century -- New York (State) -- New York; Artists as authors -- New York (State) -- New York; Authors -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Art -- Economic aspects; Art, Abstract -- New York (State) -- New York
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Sketchbooks; Sound recordings; Works of art; Scrapbooks
Provenance
Charles Green Shaw bequeathed his scrapbooks to the Archives of American Art in 1974. The remaining papers were a gift of his estate in 1975.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Alternative Forms Available
A few photographs of Shaw's paintings, exhibition catalogs, and his published children's book It Looked Like Spilt Milk, are available on microfilm reel 75.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Information, 1874-1970, Series 1:; (Boxes 1, 46, OV 50; 0.2 linear ft.)
  Family documents consist of receipts for stock purchases and dividends paid and Shaw's father's passport; also included are his uncle, Frank D. Shaw's, diplomas and reports to the Larchmont Yacht Club.
  Biographical information is arranged alphabetically by subject and chronologically within folders.
  - Awards and Certificates, 1969-1970, undated, (see also Box 46) (Box 1)
  - Biographical Notes, 1946-1968, undated (Box 1)
  - Birth Certificate, 1921 (Box 1)
  - Family Documents (Box 1)
    - Charles G. Shaw (father), 1865-1871 (Box 1)
    - Charles G. Shaw (father), 1898, (see also Box 46) (Box 1)
    - Frank D. Shaw (uncle), 1892-1895 (Box 1)
    - Frank D. Shaw (uncle), 1874-1878, (see also OV 50) (Box 1)
  - Identification Cards, 1966, undated (Box 1)
  - Memberships, 1930-1972, undated, (see also: Box 46) (Box 1)
  - Military Records, 1916-1943, undated (Box 1)
  - Passport; Alien Registration (U.K.), 1920-1921 (Box 1)
  - Oversized Awards and Certificates (Columbia Institute), 1905, (see also Box 1) (Box 46 (sol))
  - Oversized Diplomas (Yale University; Signal Corps Aviation School), 1914, 1917 (Box 46 (sol))
  - Oversized Family Documents, 1898, (see also Box 1, OV 50) (Box 46 (sol))
  - Oversized Memberships (Delta Psi Fraternity), undated, (see also Box 1) (Box 46 (sol))
  - Oversized Family Documents, 1874-1878, (see also Boxes 1, 46) (Box OV 50)
- Correspondence, 1833-1973, Series 2:; (Boxes 1-3; 2.5 linear ft.)
  The series is arranged as 2 subseries:
  2.1: Charles Green Shaw, 1909-1973
  2.1: Family Correspondence, 1833-1888
  - Charles Green Shaw, A-Z, 1909-1973, 2.1:
    Charles Green Shaw's correspondence documents his personal and professional life. It consists mainly of incoming letters with some drafts and a few carbon copies of outgoing letters. While Shaw was away at school, in the service during World War I, and during extended stays in England and France soon after the War and in the early 1930s, his uncle and brother wrote frequently of everyday life at home. Letters from friends and acquaintances provide a glimpse of Shaw's life as a "man about town" as do many surviving love letters. Other correspondence concerns his careers as an artist, writer and illustrator.
    The alphabetized portion of Shaw's correspondence includes a small amount of correspondence with individuals of note, among them Adele Astair, Clarence and Ruby Darrow, F. Scott Fitzgerald, John D. Graham, Anita and John Loos, H. L. Mencken, Robert C. Osborn, Cole Porter, Carl Van Vechten, and Walter Winchell.
    Many of Shaw's sketchbooks arranged in Series 4 also contain drafts of letters.
    The majority of the correspondence is arranged chronologically, though a much smaller quantity of correspondence with notable individuals has been separated and is arranged alphabetically.
    - Astair, Adele, 1927, undated (Box 1)
    - Carroll, Jane, 1922-1923, undated (Box 1)
    - Darrow, Clarence and Ruby, 1927-1928 (Box 1)
    - Fitzgerald, F. Scott, 1927 (Box 1)
    - Graham, John D., 1938, 1949 (Box 1)
    - Lehmann, Rosamund, 1927 (Box 1)
    - Loos, Anita and John, 1928-1931, undated (Box 1)
    - Mencken, H. L., 1925-1942 (Box 1)
    - Morgan, Helen, 1927, undated (Box 1)
    - Osborn, Robert C., undated (Box 1)
    - Porter, Cole, 1922-1959, undated (Box 1)
    - Strange, Michael, undated (Box 1)
    - Van Vechten, Carl, 1928 (Box 1)
    - Winchell, Walter, 1931 (Box 1)
    - Chronological Correspondence, 1909-1918, (13 folders) (Box 1)
    - Chronological Correspondence, 1918-1973, (22 folders) (Box 2)
    - Chronological Correspondence, undated, (11 folders) (Box 3)
  - Family Correspondence, 1833-1888, 2.2:
    Correspondence found here primarily concerns business and family matters. Correspondents represented are Charles G. Shaw, Sr. and Jr.(Shaw's grandfather and father), David Shaw, Frank Shaw, George W. Shaw, and Sallie Carr Shaw (Shaw's grandmother).
    - Correspondence, 1833-1888, undated, (3 folders) (Box 3)
- Writings, 1910-1971, Series 3:; (Boxes 3-20, 46; 17.5 linear ft.)
  3.1: Writings By Shaw, 1910-1971
  3.2: Writings By Other Authors, 1911-circa 1969
  - Writings by Shaw, 1910-1971, 3.1:
    Writings by Shaw include diaries, fiction and non-fiction, notes, plays, poems, quizzes, and short writings. The diaries (145 volumes) contain daily one-page entries that note rising and bedtimes, hours spent writing or painting, social engagements and business appointments. People are usually identified by initials only. Among the notes are notebooks (17 volumes) that include travel observations, notes on restaurants and nightclubs, notes for fiction and miscellaneous notes such as journal entries and quotations. Quizzes were featured in Shaw's newspaper column. Short writings were mainly "fillers" for magazines; these often consist of lists of details about various subjects or events. Some of the manuscripts, specifically children's stories, are illustrated with drawings and gouache paintings; those for books about Boston, London, New York and Paris are illustrated with photographs.
    - Diaries, 1922-1970, 3.1.1:
      - Volumes 1-4: 1 September-8 April 1923 (Box 3)
      - Volumes 5-8: 9 April 1923-31 January 1924 (Box 3)
      - Volumes 9-12: 1 February 1924-21 January 1925 (Box 3)
      - Volumes 13-16: 22 January-16 August, 21 August-23 October 1925 (Box 3)
      - Volumes 17-20: 24 October 1925-28 September 1926 (Box 3)
      - Volumes 21-24: 29 September-31 October, 5 December 1926-3 July 1927 (Box 3)
      - Volumes 25-28: 5 July 1927-9 May 1928 (Box 4)
      - Volumes 29-32: 10 May 1928-5 May 1929 (Box 4)
      - Volumes 33-34: 6 May-7 August 1929 (Box 4)
      - Volumes 35-36: 29 August-8 November 1929 (Box 4)
      - Volumes 37-38: 9 November 1929-15 April 1930 (Box 4)
      - Volumes 39-40: 16 April-21 November 1930 (Box 4)
      - Volume 41: 22 November 1930-14 February 1931 (Box 4)
      - Volumes 42-43: 15 February-11 June 1931 (Box 4)
      - Volumes 44-45: 12 June 1931-29 June 1932 (Box 4)
      - Volumes 46-47: 30 June-31 December 1932 (Box 4)
      - Volume 48: 1 January-31 March 1933 (Box 4)
      - Volume 49: 1 April-29 June 1933 (Box 4)
      - Volume 50: 4 July-21 October 1933 (Box 4)
      - Volume 51: 22 October-31 December 1933 (Box 4)
      - Volume 52: 1 January-31 March 1934 (Box 4)
      - Volume 53: 1 April-30 June 1934 (Box 4)
      - Volume 54: 1 July-30 September 1934 (Box 4)
      - Volume 55: 1 October-31 December 1934 (Box 5)
      - Volume 56: 1 January-31 May 1935 (Box 5)
      - Volume 57: 1 June-14 October 1935 (Box 5)
      - Volume 58: 15 October 1935-10 March 1936 (Box 5)
      - Volume 59: 11 March-31 May 1936 (Box 5)
      - Volume 60: 1 June-30 September 1936 (Box 5)
      - Volume 61: 1 October 1936-28 February 1937 (Box 5)
      - Volume 62: 1 March-1 June 1937 (Box 5)
      - Volume 63: 1 June-30 September 1937 (Box 5)
      - Volume 64: 1 October 1937-31 January 1938 (Box 5)
      - Volume 65: 1 February-14 June 1938 (Box 5)
      - Volume 66: 15 June-30 September 1938 (Box 5)
      - Volume 67: 1 October 1938-20 February 1939 (Box 5)
      - Volume 68: 21 February-14 July 1939 (Box 6)
      - Volume 69: 15 July-30 November 1939 (Box 6)
      - Volume 70: 1 December 1939-30 April 1940 (Box 6)
      - Volume 71: 1 May-30 September 1940 (Box 6)
      - Volume 72: 1 October 1940-28 February 1941 (Box 6)
      - Volume 73: 1 March-31 July 1941 (Box 6)
      - Volume 74: 1 August-31 December 1941 (Box 6)
      - Volume 75: 1 January-31 May 1942 (Box 6)
      - Volume 76: 1 June-31 October 1942 (Box 6)
      - Volume 77: 1 November 1942-30 March 1943 (Box 6)
      - Volume 78: 1 April 31-August 1943 (Box 6)
      - Volume 79: 1 September 1943-31 January 1944 (Box 6)
      - Volume 80: 1 February-30 June 1944 (Box 7)
      - Volume 81: 1 July-30 November 1944 (Box 7)
      - Volume 82: 1 December 1944-30 April 1945 (Box 7)
      - Volume 83: 1 May-30 September 1945 (Box 7)
      - Volume 84: 1 October 1945-28 February 1946 (Box 7)
      - Volume 85: 1 March-31 July 1946 (Box 7)
      - Volume 86: 1 August-31 December 1946 (Box 7)
      - Volume 87: 1 January-31 May 1947 (Box 7)
      - Volume 88: 1 June-31 October 1947 (Box 7)
      - Volume 89: 1 November 1947-14 January 1948 (Box 7)
      - Volume 90: 15 January-31 March 1948 (Box 7)
      - Volume 91: 1 April-31 August 1948 (Box 7)
      - Volume 92: 1 September 1948-31 January 1949 (Box 8)
      - Volume 93: 1 February-30 June 1949 (Box 8)
      - Volume 94: 1 July-30 November 1949 (Box 8)
      - Volume 95: 1 December 1949-30 April 1950 (Box 8)
      - Volume 96: 1 May-30 September 1950 (Box 8)
      - Volume 97: 1 October 1950-28 February 1951 (Box 8)
      - Volume 98: 1 March-31 July 1951 (Box 8)
      - Volume 99: 1 August-31 December 1951 (Box 8)
      - Volume 100: 1 January-31 May 1952 (Box 8)
      - Volume 101: 1 June-31 October 1952 (Box 8)
      - Volume 102: 1 November 1952-31 March 1953 (Box 8)
      - Volume 103: 1 April-31 August 1953 (Box 8)
      - Volume 104: 6 September 1953-31 January 1954 (Box 9)
      - Volume 105: 1 February-30 June 1954 (Box 9)
      - Volume 106: 1 July-30 November 1954 (Box 9)
      - Volume 107: 1 December 1954-30 April 1955 (Box 9)
      - Volume 108: 1 May-20 September 1955 (Box 9)
      - Volume 109: 1 October 1955-28 February 1956 (Box 9)
      - Volume 110: 1 March-30 July 1956 (Box 9)
      - Volume 111: 1 August-31 December 1956 (Box 9)
      - Volume 112: 1 January-31 May 1957 (Box 9)
      - Volume 113: 1 June-31 October 1957 (Box 9)
      - Volume 114: 1 November 1957-31 March 1958 (Box 9)
      - Volume 115: 1 April-31 August 1958 (Box 9)
      - Volume 116: 1 September 1958-31 January 1959 (Box 10)
      - Volume 117: 1 February-30 June 1959 (Box 10)
      - Volume 118: 1 July-30 November 1959 (Box 10)
      - Volume 119: 1 December 1959-30 April 1960 (Box 10)
      - Volume 120: 1 May-30 September 1960 (Box 10)
      - Volume 121: 1 October 1960-28 February 1961 (Box 10)
      - Volume 122: 1 March-31 July 1961 (Box 10)
      - Volume 123: 1 August-31 December 1961 (Box 10)
      - Volume 124: 1 January-31 May 1962 (Box 10)
      - Volume 125: 1 June-31 October 1962 (Box 10)
      - Volume 126: 1 November 1962-31 March 1963 (Box 10)
      - Volume 127: 1 April-31 August 1963 (Box 10)
      - Volume 128: 1 September 1963-31 January 1964 (Box 10)
      - Volume 129: 1 February-30 June 1964 (Box 11)
      - Volume 130: 1 July-30 November 1964 (Box 11)
      - Volume 131: 1 December 1964-30 April 1965 (Box 11)
      - Volume 132: 1 May-30 September 1965 (Box 11)
      - Volume 133: 1 October 1965-28 February 1966 (Box 11)
      - Volume 134: 1 March-30 June 1966 (Box 11)
      - Volume 135: 1 July-30 November 1966 (Box 11)
      - Volume 136: 1 December 1966-30 April 1967 (Box 11)
      - Volume 137: 1 May-30 September 1967 (Box 11)
      - Volume 138: 1 October 1967-28 February 1968 (Box 11)
      - Volume 139: 1 March-30 June 1968 (Box 11)
      - Volume 140: 1 July-30 November 1968 (Box 11)
      - Volume 141: 1 December 1968-30 April 1969 (Box 11)
      - Volume 142: 1 May-30 September 1969 (Box 12)
      - Volume 143: 1 October 1969-28 February 1970 (Box 12)
      - Volume 144: 1 March-31 July 1970 (Box 12)
      - Volume 145: 1 August-31 December 1970 (Box 12)
    - Fiction, circa 1920s-circa 1970, 3.1.2:
      - "The Adventures of Hally," undated (Box 12)
      - "At the Bijou Palace," undated (Box 12)
      - "The Birthday of the Moon," undated (Box 12)
      - "Conclusions of a Man with Blue Spectacles," undated (Box 12)
      - "The Cynic," undated (Box 12)
      - "Dead," undated (Box 12)
      - "A Dismal Afternoon," undated (Box 12)
      - "Early American," undated (Box 12)
      - "Everything Has a Color," undated (Box 12)
      - "The Giant of Central Park," undated, (illustrated) (Box 12)
      - "The Inconsistency of Father Andrew by Ennismore Green," undated, (illustrated) (Box 12)
      - "Jumble Pie," undated, (3 folders; illustrated) (Box 12)
      - "Just Doggerel," undated, (illustrated) (Box 12)
      - "Lady of Leisure," undated (Box 12)
      - "The Lone Wolf," undated, (3 folders; draft, corrected manuscript, synopsis, chapter summaries, and notes) (Box 12)
      - "The Marvelous Mirror," undated (Box 12)
      - "A Night 'Round the Town," undated (Box 12)
      - "No Such Animal," undated, (illustrated) (Box 12)
      - "The Nonsense Noisy Book," undated (Box 13)
      - "Nonsense on the Half Shell," undated, (illustrated) (Box 13)
      - "One Hundred Fables for Children of Any Age Under One Hundred Years," undated (Box 13)
      - "Pitter Patter" (a story in pictures), undated (Box 13)
      - "A Rainy Afternoon," undated (Box 13)
      - "Sunrise and Sunset," undated, (illustrated) (Box 13)
      - "The Tale of a Kite," undated, (illustrated) (Box 13)
      - "The Tale of a Tadpole," undated (Box 13)
      - "The Tale of the Two Little Tibbs," undated (Box 13)
      - "The Tale of the Two Little Twinkles," undated (Box 13)
      - "The Town that Wouldn't Change," undated (Box 13)
      - "Toy Parade" (a story in pictures), 1946 (Box 13)
      - "Twenty-one West 58th Street," undated (Box 13)